[ Music ]
[ 音乐 ]
[ Applause ]
[ 掌声 ]
&gt;&gt; Good morning everyone.
&gt;&gt; 大家早上好
My name is Karol Gasinski, and I
我叫 Karol Gasinski 我是
am a member of GPU Software
GPU 软件架构组的成员
We will start this session with
在本次会议的开头
a brief summary of what is new
我们将简单概括
in [inaudible], in terms of VR
macOS 中的新功能 主要和 VR 的应用有关
Then, we will take a deep dive
然后 我们将深入探讨
into a new Metal 2 features,
Metal 2 的新特性
designs specifically for the VR
它是今年
this year.
专为 VR 而设计的
And finally, we will end this
最后 在本次会议的结尾
session with advanced techniques
我们将讨论
for developing VR applications.
开发 VR App 的先进技术
Recently, we introduced new iMac
近来 我们推出了全新的 iMac 和 iMac Pro
and iMac Pro that have great
这两款产品使用了强大的
GPUs on board; iMac is now
图形处理器
equipped with [inaudible] based
iMac 如今配有基于 ARM 的
GPUs and have up to 80 gigabytes
图形处理器 并且拥有最高 8 GB
of video memory on board.
的视频存储器
While iMac Pro are equipped with
而 iMac Pro 配有
even more advanced and even
更先进且更大的
bigger based GPUs, with up to 16
图形处理器 视频存储器容量最高可达 16 GB
That's a lot of power that is
这是多么强大的功能
now in your hands.
现在就掌握在大家的手中
But we are not limiting our
但我们并没有
service to iMac on their own.
将服务限制在 iMac 上
With recent announcement of
我们最近宣布
extended GPU support, you can
扩展了图形处理器支持 这能让你
now turn any Mac into powerful
将任何一台 Mac 变成强大的工作站
workstation that gives you more
它将赋予你超过
than 10 [inaudible] of
10 倍更强大的
processing power.
处理能力
And that's not all.
我们做的还不止这些
Today we are introducing plug
今天我们介绍的是
and play support for HTC Vive
HTC Vive 这款头戴式显示器
head mounted display.
的即插即用支持
It has two panels with 1,440 by
它有两块 1440x1600
1,600 and 650 pixels per inch.
AMOLED 的屏幕和每英寸 615 像素
That's 78% increase in the
和 Vive 相比
resolution, and 57% increase in
分辨率提高了百分之 78
pixel density compared to Vive.
像素密度提高了百分之 57
And with support for better
更强大的屏幕
panels comes support for its new
为它的新前置双摄像头系统
dual-camera front-facing system,
提供了支持
so developers will now be able
这样 开发者们就可以
to use those cameras to
用这些摄像头
experiment with pass-through
在 Mac 上
video on Mac.
尝试直通视频
And together with Vive Pro
同时加上 Vive Pro 的支持
support comes improved tracking
就得到了更加先进的跟踪系统
So, you might be wondering how
那么 你现在可能想知道如何
you can start developing VR
在 macOS 上
application on Mac OS.
开始 VR App 的开发
Both HTC Vive and Vive Pro work
HTC Vive 和 Vive Pro
in conjunction with Valve
同时能和 Valve 的
SteamVR runtime, that provides a
SteamVR Runtime 一起运行 这能提供
number of services including VR
大量的服务 其中就包括 VR 生成器
Valve is also making open VR
Valve 也能让开放的 VR
framework that is available on
框架运行于 macOS 上
Mac OS, so that you can do the
这样你就能通过 SteamVR 建立地图
We've been working very closely
我们一直和 Valve 以及 HTC 紧密合作
sure that Vive Pro is supported
确保 Vive Pro 在 macOS 上的
in SteamVR runtime on Mac OS.
SteamVR Runtime 中获得支持
So, now let's see how new Metal
那么 接下来我们来了解一下
features that we're introducing
我们现在正在介绍的 Metal 新功能
can develop a [inaudible] Mac OS
会如何开发 macOS Mojave 可以用来
fiber-optimize your VR
优化你的 VR App 的品质
As a quick refresher, let's
为了帮助大家回忆 让我们
review current interaction
回顾一下当下
between application and VR
App 和 VR 生成器之间的交互
Application will start by
App 在启动时会
rendering image for left and
将针对左眼和右眼的图像
right eye into 30 multi-sample
转换为 30 个多样本纹理
Then it will resolve those
然后它会将这些图像分解成
images into iOS surface back
iOS 表面背景纹理
textures that can be further
它可以进一步
passed to VR compositor.
传递给 VR 生成器
VR compositor will perform final
VR 生成器将会执行最终
processing step that will
处理步骤
include [inaudible] distortion
其中包括镜头失真校正
aberration, and order
色差调整以及排序操作
We can call it in short warp.
简单来说就是变形
Once the final image is
最终图像一旦生成
produced, it can be sent to the
就会被发送到
headset for presentment.
头戴式设备或呈现的画面之中
It is a lot of work here that is
这里涉及的很多操作
happening twice, so let's see if
会发生两次 让我们来看一下
you can do something about that.
你可不可以对此做些什么
See, now with VR application it
看 如今有了 VR App
wants to benefit from
它想要从多样本中获益
needed to use the dedicated
它需要针对每只眼睛使用
textures per i, or single shared
专用纹理 或者都使用
one, for both.
单一的共享纹理
But none of those layouts is
但是这些布局都并不完美
The dedicated textures require
专用纹理需要
separate draw calls and passes,
独立的绘图调用和通道
as we just saw.
这正如我们所见
While straight textures enable
而直接纹理可以
rendering of both eyes in single
在单一渲染和结果通道中
rendered and results pass, they
进行双眼的渲染
are problematic when it comes to
这些纹理在
post-processing the effects.
后期处理和效果方面会产生一些问题
[Inaudible] textures have all
对于分层纹理拥有
the benefits of both dedicated
专用纹理和共享布局
and shared layouts, but
的全部优势 但是
currently they couldn't be used
当下它们不能和多重采样抗锯齿一起使用
This was forcing app developers
这促使 App 开发者们
to use different rendering
使用不同的渲染兼用布局
part-time layouts, based on the
具体取决于
fact if they wanted to use MSAA
他们是否想使用多重采样抗锯齿
Or use different tricks to work
或使用不同诀窍来解决这一问题
So let's see how we can optimize
那么我们就来看看 我们可以如何优化
this rendering.
这一渲染
Today, we introduce new texture
今天我们要介绍
types to the multi-sample
一个新的纹理
already textured.
2DMultisampleArray 纹理
This texture type has all the
这一纹理类型拥有
benefits of previously mentioned
上述类型的所有优点
types without any of the
而没有上述类型的任何缺点
Thanks to that it is now
多亏有了它
possible to separate from each
现在可以区分每一
other rendering space, which
渲染空间
simplifies the post-processing
这简化了后期处理
effects, views count, so that
效果 视图数
application can fall back easily
这样 App 就可以
to monoscope rendering and
轻松地返回单视场渲染
control over anti-aliasing mode.
并能控制抗锯齿模式
As a result, application can now
作为结果 App 就能
have single rendering files that
拥有单一渲染文件
can be easily adopted to any
可以轻松运用于任何情形之中
situation, and most important,
最重要的是
that can be rendered with single
在每种情景中 App 可以
draw and render pass in each
通过单一绘图和渲染通道
case.
被渲染
So here we see code snippet for
那么这里我们可以看到
creation of mentioned 2D multi
创建上述 2DMultisampleArray
sample [inaudible] texture.
纹理的代码片段
We set up sample count to 4, as
我们将样本数设置为 4
it's an optimal tradeoff between
这样就能在质量和性能之间
quality and performance, and at
达到最佳平衡
the same time, we set up our
与此同时 我们将
other length to 2 as we want to
其他长度设置为 2 因为我们想
store each image for each I in
将每只眼睛的图像存储为
separate slice.
独立的切片
So let's see how our pipeline
那么让我们让来看看 管线会怎样
will change.
发生变化
We can now replace those 2D
我们现在可以将那些 2D
multi-sample textures with
多样本纹理用
single 2D multi-sample
单一 2D 多样本阵列纹理
[inaudible] one.
纹理进行替换
So now application can render
那么现在 App 就能
both I in single render pass and
在单一渲染通道进行双眼渲染
if it's using instancing, it can
而且如果它使用实例化
even do that in single draw
它甚至可以在单一绘图代码中
code.
做到这一点
So that already looks great, but
这已经看起来很不错了
we still need to resolve those
但是我们仍然需要将那些
2D multi-sample array texture
2D 多样本阵列纹理切片
slices into separate iOS
变为独立的 iOS
[inaudible] faces before we pass
面部图像在我们将其传递到
them to compositor.
生成器之前
So let's focus on our way,
那么让我们专注于我们自己的方式
application shares textures with
App 和生成器
compositor.
共享纹理
So now, for sharing textures, we
那么现在 为了共享纹理
use IOSurfaces.
我们使用 IOSurface
They are sharing textures
它们在不同的进程空间
between different process spaces
和不同的图形处理器之间
and different GPUs, that we've
共享纹理 但是有着这样的
got [inaudible] comes a price.
灵活性会产生代价
IOSurfaces can be only used to
IOSurface 只可用于
share simple 2D textures, so if
共享简单的 2D 纹理
you have a multi-sampled one,
所以如果你有多样本纹理
storing [inaudible] or having
存储困难或者拥有
[inaudible], they couldn't be
复杂的纹理 它们不能被共享
That's why today we introduce
这就是为什么我们今天要介绍
shareable Metal textures that
可共享的 Metal 纹理
allow your applications to share
他们能让你的 App
any type of Metal texture
在进程空间之间共享
between process spaces, as long
任意一种 Metal 纹理
as these textures stay in scope
只要这些纹理位于
of single GPU.
单一图形处理器之中
This file features [inaudible]
这个文件的特色是
advanced view of these cases.
这些案例的高级视图
For example, sharing depth of
例如 将场景的深度
your scene with VR compositor.
和 VR 生成器进行共享
But, of course, it's not limited
但是 当然并不仅限于此
Now, let's look how those
现在让我们看看如何
textures can be created.
来创建那些纹理
Because shareable textures
因为可共享的纹理
allows us now to pass complex
能让我们在进程之间
textures between processes, we
传递复杂纹理 所以我们
will create 2D array texture
会创建 2D 阵列纹理
that we will pass to VR
我们会将其传递给 VR 生成器
As you can see, to do that, we
如你所见 我们为此
use new methods, new shared
使用了新方式
texture with this creator.
用这个创建工具创建了新的共享纹理
And while doing that, you need
与此同时
to remember to use private
你必须记得使用
storage mode, as this texture
Private 存储模式
can be only accessed by the GPU
这一纹理仅能通过将其创建出来的
on which it was created.
图形处理器获得
Now, we see a code snippet
现在我们可以看到一个代码片段
showing us how our VR
向我们展示了以前我们的 VR
application would send IOSurface
App 会如何将 IOSurface
to VR compositor in the past.
发送到 VR 生成器
We will now go through this code
我们现在来看看这个代码片段
snippet, and see what changes
看看需要做出哪些改变
needs to be applied to switch
从而可以从使用 IOSurface
from using IOSurfaces to shared
转变为共享的 Metal 纹理
So we don't need those two
所以我们无须再使用这两个
IOSurfaces anymore, and those
IOSurface 而且由它们
two textures that were backed by
支持的两种纹理
them can now be replaced with
现在可以被替换为
single shareable Metal texture
单一可共享 Metal 纹理
that is over 2D array type.
这就是目前的 2D 阵列纹理
We will then assign this texture
然后我们会将这一纹理分配给
to both texture descriptors from
来自开放式 VRSDK
open VRSDK, and change its type
的两个纹理描述器 并将它的类型
from IOSurface to Metal.
从 IOSurface 改变为 Metal
After doing these few changes,
在完成这几项改变之后
we can submit image for the left
我们可以将针对
and right I to the compositor.
左眼和右眼的图像 提交至生成器
Compositor will now know that
然后生成器就会知道 我们已经传递了
texture with advanced layout,
拥有高级布局的 Metal 纹理
instead of IOSurface, and if we
而非 IOSurface 而且当我们
check, if its type is 2D array
查看的时候 如果它的类型是 2D 阵列纹理
or 2D multi-sampling array.
或者 2D 多样本阵列纹理
If it is, then compositor will
如果是这样 那么生成器将
automatically assume that image
自动认定
for the left i is stored in
对于左眼的图像存储于
slice 0, and image for right i
切片 0 之中 对于右眼的图像
is stored in slice 1.
存储于 切片 1 之中
So your application doesn't need
这样你的 App 就无须
to do anything more about that.
再对此做任何其他操作
And of course, sharing Metal
当然 在 App
textures between application and
和生成器之间
compositor is not the only use
共享 Metal
case for shareable Metal
并非是 Metal 纹理的唯一用法
So here we have simple example
这里有几个简单的例子
of how you can pass Metal
展现了你可以如何
texture between any two
在任意两个进程之间
processes.
传递 Metal 纹理
So we start exactly in the same
那么我们完全按照同样的方式开始
We create our shareable Metal
我们创建我们的可共享 Metal 纹理
texture, but now from this
但如今我们从这一纹理中
texture, we create special
创建出了可以在
shared texture handle that can
进程空间之间传递的
be passed between process spaces
特殊共享纹理句柄
using cross-process
可以通过跨进程
communication connection.
通信连接
Once this handle is passed to
一旦这一句柄被传递至
other process, it can be used to
其他进程 它就可以用于
recreate texture object.
重新创建纹理对象
But while doing that, you need
但在做此的同时 你必须
to remember to recreate your
记得在与其他进程空间中
texture object on exactly the
进行创建时
same device as it was originally
所使用的相同设备上
created in other process space,
重新创建你的纹理对象
as this texture cannot leave
因为这一纹理不能脱离
scope of GPU.
图形处理器的范围
So now let's get back to our
现在我们再回过来看我们的管线
pipeline and see what will
看看会发生什么变化
change.
现在 App 可以
those separate IOSurfaces with
用一个 2D 阵列纹理
one 2D array texture, storing
替换那些分离的 IOSurface
the image for both i's.
将针对双眼的图像存储起来
This allows further optimization
这能够促成进一步的优化
as original 2D multi-sample
因为原始的 2D 多样本
array texture can be now
阵列纹理现在也可以
resolved in one pass as well to
在一个通道中加以解决
just create it shareable through
只需通过阵列纹理
the array texture.
将其创建成可共享的类型即可
But that's not everything.
而且不止如此
Let's look at the compositor.
让我们来看一下生成器
Once we have simplified
一旦我们在 App 上
rendering parts on application
完成了渲染部件的简化
site, there is nothing
就没有什么
preventing compositor from
可以阻止生成器
benefiting from those new
从这些新特性中获益
So compositor can now use those
所以生成器现在可以使用
incoming 2D array textures and
这些即将发布的 2D 阵列纹理
perform work for both i's in
并能在单一渲染通道中
single render pass as well.
针对双眼执行操作
And as you can see, we've just
正如你所见 我们刚刚完成了
simplified the whole pipeline.
整条管线的简化
So let's do recap of what we've
那么让我们来总结一下
just learned.
我们刚刚了解到的内容
We've just described two new
我们刚刚描述了两种新的
Metal features.
Metal 纹理
Shareable Metal textures, and 2D
可共享 Metal 纹理以及
multi-sample array texture type.
2D 多样本阵列纹理
And the way they can be used to
以及用他们来
further optimize your rendering
进一步优化你的渲染管线
pipeline.
的方式
Both features will be soon
这两种纹理马上就会
supported in upcoming SteamVR
在即将推出的 SteamVR
runtime updates.
Runtime 更新中获得支持
So now, let's focus on
那么现在让我们把注意力集中在
techniques that will allow your
那些可以将你 App 的
application to maximize its CPU
中央处理器和图形处理器的使用
and GPU utilization.
最大化的技术之上
We will divide this section into
这一部分我们会分为
two subsections-- Advanced frame
两个小节 先进的帧同步技术
pacing and a reducing free rate.
以及不断降低的空闲率
We will start with frame pacing.
我们先来讲讲帧同步技术
And in this section, we will
在这一小节中
analyze application frame pacing
我们将分析 App 的帧同步技术
and how it can be optimized for
以及如何为了 VR 优化帧同步技术
So let's start with simple,
那么我们先从简单的
single-threaded application that
单线程 App 入手
is executing everything in
它们在执行所有操作时都会
serial monitoring.
采取串口监视的方式
Such application will start its
这样的 App 会通过调用 WaitGet 停顿
frame by calling WaitGet pauses,
开始处理其中的画面
to receive pauses, and
从而接收停顿
synchronize its execution to the
并将其执行情况同步到
frame rate of the headset.
头戴式设备的帧率之中
Both Vive and Vive Pro has
Vive 和 Vive Pro 都拥有
refresh rate of 90 frames per
每秒 90 帧的刷新率
second, which means the
这就意味着
application has only 11.1
App 只需要 11.1
milliseconds to process the
毫秒就能处理一帧
For comparison, blink of an eye
对比之下 眨一下眼
takes about 300 milliseconds.
大约需要 300 毫秒
So in this time, the application
那么在这一时间里
should render 50 frames.
App 就能渲染 50 帧画面
So once our application receives
所以一旦 App 收到了
pauses from WaitGet pauses, it
来自 WaitGet 停顿的停顿
can start simulation of your
它就能开始模拟你的试验
When this simulation is
一旦完成模拟
complete, and state of all
也就知道了
objects is known, application
所有对象的状态
can continue with encoding
App 就能继续对
command buffer that will be then
命令缓冲区进行编码
sent to GPU for execution.
然后将其发送至图形处理器 以实现执行目的
Once GPU is done, an image for
一旦图形处理器完成操作
both i's is rendered, it can be
针对双眼的图像 也就渲染完成了
sent to VR compositor for final
它可以被发送至 VR 生成器
post-processing, as we talked
进行我们在前几张幻灯片中所讲的
about a few slides before.
最终后期处理
After that, frames scanned out
然后再从存储器中
from memory to [inaudible] in
将各帧图像扫描到 头戴式设备的面板中
This transfer takes additional
这一传输需要额外的帧
frame as all pixels need to be
因为在呈现图像之前
updated before image can be
所有像素必须完成更新
Once all pixels are updated,
一旦所有像素完成更新
[inaudible] and user can see a
头戴式设备的面板中和用户 可以看到
frame.
一帧图像
So as you can see from the
所以你可以看到
moment the application receives
从 App 收到停顿的那一刻起
pauses, to the moment image is
到图像真正投射出来
really projected, it takes about
的那一刻为止 一共历时 25 毫秒
That is why application receives
这就是为什么 App 要接收
pauses that are already
已经预测到
predicted into the future, to
会在未来发生的停顿
the moment when photons will be
到了发射光子的那一刻
emitted, so that the rendered
就可以使被渲染的
image is matching the user
图像可以和用户的停顿相匹配
pause.
而这一连串
overlapping with previous and
与上一帧以及下一帧
next frame is creating our frame
重叠的事件创建了我们的
basing diagram.
帧基础图
As you can see, in case of the
如你所见
single-threaded application, GPU
在单线程 App 中 图形处理器
is idle most of the time.
在大部分时间中都是空闲的
So let's see if we can do
那就让我们来看看
anything about that.
是否可以对此做些什么
We are now switching to
我们现在切换到了
multi-threaded application,
多线程 App
which separates simulation of
它将视觉环境的模拟
its visual environment from
和针对图形处理器的编码操作
encoding operations to the GPU.
分离开来
Encoding of those operations
对于这些操作的编码
will now happen on separate
现在会在独立的
rendering threads.
渲染线程中进行
Because we've separated
因为我们已将模拟
simulation from encoding,
和编码分离开来
simulation for our frame can
所以对于帧的模拟
happen in parallel to previous
可与图形处理器操作
frame encoding of GPU
的上一帧编码
operations.
同时进行
This means that encoding is now
这意味着编码现在
shifted area in time, and starts
已经在时间上发生了变化
immediately after we receive
在我们收到预测的停顿之后
predicted pauses.
编码会立即开始
This means that your application
这意味着你的 App
will now have more time to
现在可以有更多时间
encode the GPU [inaudible] and
对图形处理器进行编码
GPU will have more time to
并且图形处理器也可以有更多时间
process it.
来处理它
So, as a result, your
这样一来 你的 App 可以拥有更好的
visualize.
视觉化效果
But there is one trick.
但这里有一点要注意
Because simulation is now
因为现在模拟
happening one frame in advance,
会在上一帧就开始
it requires separate set of
所以需要独立的一组
predicted pauses.
预测停顿
This set is predicted 56
这一组可以预测到
milliseconds into the future so
未来的 56 毫秒
that it will match the set
这样就能和针对渲染线程
predicted for rendering thread
进行预测的小组相匹配
and both will match the moment
而且这两组会
when photons are emitted.
和发射光子的时刻相匹配
This diagram already looks good
这张图从中央处理器来看
from CPU side, as we can see
已经很不错了 正如我们所见
application is nicely
App 在中央处理器中
distributing its work
很好的分配了它的工作 但是
let's focus on GPU.
让我们把重点放在图形处理器上
As you can see, now our example
如你所见 我们例子中的 App
application is encoding all
现在正在对所有这些图形处理器
these GPU [inaudible] for the
所有工作流程进行编码
whole frame into a single common
从而使一帧进入单一的公用缓冲区
buffer, so unless this common
因此除非这一公用缓冲区已完成
buffer is complete, GPU is
否则图形处理器就会
waiting idle.
处于空闲的等待状态
But it's important to notice
不过 值得注意的是
that encoding of GPU operations
在中央处理器上 对图形处理器的操作
on a CPU takes much less time
进行编码所花费的时间
than processing of these
比在图形处理器上处理这些操作
operations on the GPU.
所花费的时间要少很多
So we can benefit from this
因此我们可以利用这一事实
fact, and split our encoding
并将我们的编码操作
operation into a few common
分解成为几个公用缓冲区
buffers while a few common
而几个公用缓冲区
buffer will be encoded very
可以进行快速编码
fast, with just few operations,
仅需几步操作而已
and submitted to GPU as fast as
并尽快将其提交至
possible.
图形处理器
This way, now our encoding is
这样一来 我们就能
processing in parallel to GPU
在图形处理器已经处理帧的同时
already processing our frame,
进行我们的编码
and as you can see, we've just
而且如你所见
extended the time when GPU is
在图形处理器进行处理的时候
doing its work, and as a result,
我们延长了时间
further increase amount of work
作为结果 这样进一步增加了
that you can submit in a frame.
你可以在一帧中提交的工作量
Now, let's get back to our
现在让我们回到我们的图表
diagram, and see how it all
看一下全部放在一起
looks together.
看起来会如何
So as you can see, now both CPU
如你所见 现在中央处理器
and GPU are fully utilized.
和图形处理器都被完全利用起来了
So [inaudible] application is
那么这样的 App 已经
already very good example of
为你的 App 提供了
your application, but there are
很好的示范
still few things we can do.
但我们仍有提升的空间
If you will notice, rendering
你可能会注意到
thread is still waiting with
在收到预测停顿之前
encoding of any type of GPU work
当对任何种类的图形处理器 进行编码时
before it will receive predicted
渲染线程仍然处于等待状态
But not all [inaudible] in the
但是并非一帧里的所有工作流程
frame requires those pauses.
都需要这些停顿
So let's analyze in more detail
那么让我们进行更加细致的分析
to pick our frame workloads.
来选择帧的工作负荷
Here, you can see a list of
在这里 你可以看到
workloads that may be executed
工作负荷列表 它们可能会在每一帧中被执行
Part of them happen in screen
其中一部分在屏幕空间中进行
space or require general
或者需要了解
knowledge about pause for which
与为了渲染帧所产生的停顿
frame is rendered.
有关的总体信息
We call such workloads
我们将这样的工作负荷
pause-dependent ones.
称为停顿依赖性工作负荷
At the same time, there are
与此同时
workloads that are generic and
还有一般性的
can be executed without
无需与停顿有关的信息
knowledge about pauses
就能立即执行的工作负荷
We call those workloads pause
我们将这些工作负荷称为
independent ones.
非停顿依赖性工作负荷
So currently, our application
那么现在 我们的 App
was waiting for pauses to encode
正在等待停顿
any type of work to GPU.
以对图形处理器的任何工作进行编码
But if we split those workloads
但如果我们将这些工作负荷平分开来
in half, we can encode pause
我们就能立即
independent workloads
对非停顿依赖性工作负荷编码
immediately and then wait for
然后等待停顿
pauses to continue with encoding
以继续对停顿依赖性工作负荷编码
In this slide, we've already
在这张幻灯片中 我们已经
separated pause independent
将非停顿依赖性工作负荷
workloads from pause dependent
与停顿依赖性工作负荷
ones.
区分来开
Pause independent workloads is
非停顿依赖性工作负荷
now encoded in [inaudible]
现在已经在公用缓冲区
common buffer, and is marked
被编码 如果将它和后面的停顿依赖性
with a little bit darker shade
工作负荷比较的话
than pause-dependent workload
它被标记地
following it.
要更暗一些
Because pause-independent
因为停顿依赖性工作负荷
workload can be encoded
可以被立即编码
immediately, we will do exactly
所以我们就会
that.
采取如下操作
We will encode it as soon as the
我们会在
previous frame workload is
上一帧工作负荷编码完成后
encoded.
立即对其编码
This gives CPU more time to
这给了你的中央处理器更多时间
encode the GPU work, and what is
以对图形处理器工作进行编码
even more important, it ensures
更重要的是 这确保了
us that this GPU work is already
这一图形处理器工作
waiting for being executed on
已在图形处理器上等待被执行
GPU so there will be exactly no
因此图形处理器就没有
idle time on GPU.
任何空闲时间
As soon as previous frame is
只要上一帧完成之后
finished, GPU can start with the
图形处理器就会立即开始
next one.
下一帧处理
The last subsection is a
最后一个小节就是
multi-GPU workload distribution.
多图形处理器工作负荷的分配
We can scale our workload across
我们可以在多个图形处理器之间
multiple GPUs.
分配工作负荷
Current Mac Book Pro has two GPU
当前的 Mac Book Pro 目前共有两个图形处理器
on board, and while they have
虽然它们具有
different performance
不同的性能特点
characteristics, there is
但是我们可以
nothing preventing us from using
畅通无阻地使用它们
Similarly, if each GPU is
类似地 如果每个图形处理器相互连接起来
connected, application can use
那么 App 就能用它
it for rendering to the headset
对头戴式设备进行渲染
while using Mac's primary GPU to
并同时使用 Mac 的主图形处理器
offload some work.
对一些工作进行分流
So we've just separated
所以我们将
pause-independent work and moved
停顿依赖性工作分离出来
it to a secondary GPU.
并将它移动至次图形处理器上
We could do that because it was
我们这样做是因为这些工作
already encoded much earlier in
在很久之前的帧中就已经
our frame, and now this
完成编码 而且现在
pause-independent workload is
停顿依赖性工作负荷
executing in parallel to
在执行上一帧
pause-dependent workload of
停顿依赖性工作负荷的同时 被执行
As a result, we further
因此 我们进一步
increased the amount of GPU time
增加了你在帧方面拥有的
that you had for your frame.
图形处理器时间量
But, by splitting this work into
但是 通过将这一工作分给
multiple GPUs, we now get to the
多个图形处理器 我们现在到达了
point where we need a way to
这么一种情况 我们需要一种方式
synchronize those workloads with
来将这些工作负荷
each other.
同步起来
So today we introduce new
所以我们今天要介绍新的
synchronization parameters to
同步参数
deal exactly with such
来处理这样的情况
MTL Events can now be used to
MTL Event 现在可以用于
synchronize GPU work in scope of
在不同 Metal 线索之间
single GPU across different
同步单个图形处理器范围内的
Metal cues and MTL Shared Events
图形处理器工作 而 MTL Shared Event
extends this functionality by
拓展了这一功能
allowing it to synchronize
使其可以同步
workloads across different GPUs
不同图形处理器之间
and even across different
甚至不同进程之间的工作负荷
So here we will go through the
那么在这里 我们来看看这个
simple code example.
简单的代码示例
We have our Mac, with attached
我们的 Mac 拥有
eGPU through Thunderbolt 3
外置图形处理器 它通过 Thunderbolt 3 接口
connection.
进行连接
This eGPU will be our primary
这一外置图形处理器将成为我们的
GPU driving the headset, so we
主图形处理器 用于驱动头戴式设备
can use GPU that is already in
这样我们就能使用 Mac 中
our Mac as secondary supporting
已有的图形处理器作为辅助的
GPU.
次图形处理器
And we will use shared event to
然后我们会使用共享事件来
synchronize workloads of both
同步两个图形处理器中的
GPUs.
工作负荷
Event initial value is zero, so
事件的初始值为 0
it's important to start
因此有必要
synchronization counter from 1.
从 1 开始启动同步计数器
That's because when we would
这是因为当我们
wait on just initialized event,
在初始化事件中等待之时
its counter of zero will cause
如果事件的计数器显示为 0
it to return immediately, so
事件就会立刻恢复原状
there would be no
所以就无法实现同步
So our rendering thread now
那么我们的渲染线程现在
starts encoding work for our
立即开始了针对辅助图形处理器
supporting GPU immediately.
的编码工作
It will encode pause-independent
它会对停顿依赖性工作
work that will happen on our
进行编码 这会发生在我们的
supporting GPU course, and once
次图形处理器上
this work is complete, its
一旦这一工作完成
results will be stored in locker
结果将会存储在
memory.
锁定存储器之中
That's why we follow with
这就是为什么我们采用
encoding brief operation that
编码简单操作
will transfer those results to
将这些结果传输到
system memory that is visible by
对两个图形处理器都可见
both GPUs.
的系统内存中
And once this transfer is
一旦传输完成
complete, our supporting GPU can
我们的次图形处理器就能
safely signal our shared event.
安全地向我们的共享事件发出信号
This signal will tell eGPU that
这一信号会告诉外置图形处理器
now it's safe to take those
现在接受这些结果是安全的
So our rendering thread
所以我们的渲染线程
committed this [inaudible]
执行这一些
common buffer, and supporting
共用缓冲区 并且辅助图形处理器
GPU is already processing its
已经在处理这一工作
At the same time, we can start
与此同时 我们可以开始
encoding command buffer for a
对驱动头戴式设备的
primary GPU that is driving the
主图形处理器的命令缓冲区进行编码
In this command buffer, we will
在这一命令缓冲区中
start by waiting for our shared
我们一开始会等待我们的
event to be sure that the data
共享事件 确保数据存储在
is in system memory, and once
在系统内存里
it's there, and the shared event
只要它在那里  并且共享事件
is signaled, we can perform a
收到信号 那么我们可以执行一个
brief operation that will
简单操作
transfer this data through
它会通过 Thunderbolt 3 接口
Thunderbolt 3 connection, back
将这一数据传回
to our [inaudible] GPU and once
我们的外部图形处理器中
this transfer is complete, it's
一旦传输完成
safe to perform pause-dependent
执行停顿依赖性工作就会变得安全
work, so a second command buffer
因此第二个命令缓冲区
will signal lockout event to let
就会发出封锁事件的信号
pause-dependent work know that
让停顿依赖性工作知道
it can start executing.
它可以开始执行操作了
After encoding and submitting
在将这两个命令缓冲区
those two command buffers,
编码并提交之后
rendering thread can continue as
渲染线程可以向往常一样继续
usual, with waiting for pauses,
等待停顿
and later encoding
并在之后
pause-dependent work.
对停顿依赖性工作进行编码
So now we have a mechanism to
那么现在我们就有了一个
synchronize different workloads
同步不同图形处理器间
between different GPUs.
不同工作负荷的机制
But as you can see, our
但是你可以看到
secondary GPU is still a little
我们的次图形处理器仍然
bit idle.
有些空闲
That's because in this example
这是因为在这个例子里
we decided to push through it,
我们想要设法完成
pause dependent workloads that
停顿依赖性工作负荷
have dependency with pause
即那些拥有依赖于
dependent ones.
停顿依赖性的工作
Excuse me.
抱歉
But of course there are types of
不过 当然也有一些
workloads that have no
工作负荷不具
dependencies, and they can
依赖性 它们可以
happen at lower frequencies, the
在较低频率中发生
frequency of the headset.
也就是头戴式设备的频率
One example of such workloads
这样的工作负荷
can be, for example, simulation
比如可以是
of physically based accurate
基于物理的精准
[inaudible] or anything else
异常值的模拟
that requires a lot of time to
或者需要大量更新时间
be updated.
的任何东西
Such workload can happen in the
这样的工作负荷可以发生在
background, completely
背景中 完全
asynchronously from rendering
和渲染画面不同步
frames, and each time it's
而且在它每次
ready, its results will be sent
准备完成后 它的结果就会被发送至
to primary GPU.
主图形处理器
It's marked here with gray color
这里灰色的标记
to indicate that it's not
是用来表示它
related to any particular frame.
和任何特定一帧无关
So, of course there are
那么 当然会有
different GPUs with different
具有不同性能特点的
performance characteristics, and
不同图形处理器 而且
they will have different
它们会具有不同
bandwidth connections.
带宽的连接
And your application will have
而且你的 App 将会
different workloads in a single
在一帧中拥有不同的工作负荷
frame with different relations
它们之间分别具有不同的关系
So you will need to design a way
因此你需要设计出一种方式
to distribute this workload on
让你能分配这一工作负荷
your own, but saying all that,
但是说了这么多
it's important to start thinking
开始考虑
about this GPU workload
这一图形处理器工作负荷的分配
distribution, as multi-GPU
非常重要
configuration are becoming
因为多图形处理器配置如今
common on Apple platforms.
在 Apple 应用平台上十分常见
So let's summarize everything
那么让我们来总结一下
that we've learned in this
我们在这一节中学到的
section.
所有内容
We showed multi-thread
我们展示了多线程 App
application to take full benefit
来充分利用
of all CPU codes.
所有的中央处理器代码
And split your command buffers,
并分离了命令缓冲区
to ensure that GPU is not idle.
确保图形处理器没有处于空闲状态
When doing that, if possible,
在这一过程中 在可能的条件下
try to separate
我们尽量将
pause-independent from
非停顿依赖性工作负荷
pause-dependent workloads, to be
与停顿依赖性工作负荷划分开来
able to encode this work as soon
从而尽快对这一工作进行编码
as possible, and even further,
除此之外
splitting workloads by frequency
我们还根据更新频率划分工作负荷
of update so if your application
所以如果你的 App
will execute on multi-GPU
会在多图形处理器配置下执行
configuration, you can easily
你可以轻松地
distribute it across those GPUs.
在那些图形处理器中对其进行分配
And while doing that, ensure
而且在这一过程中
that you drive each GPU with
确保你驱动各个图形处理器时
separate rendering threads to
使用了独立的渲染线程
ensure that they all execute
从而确保它们在执行时
asynchronously.
是不同步的
Now, you switch to reducing fill
现在 你来到了降低填充率的部分
Vive Pro introduces new
Vive Pro
challenges for VR application
为 VR App 的开发者带来了新挑战
To better understand scale of
为了更好地认识到
the problem, we will compare
问题的严重性 我们将比较
different medium fill rates.
不同的媒介填充率
So, for example, application
例如
rendering in default scaling
按默认缩放比例
rate to Vive headset, produces
对 Vive 头戴式设备进行渲染的 App
436 megapixels per second.
每秒可产生 4.36 亿像素
And most advanced [inaudible]
而对于目前便宜的高清屏幕相比于
against that [inaudible] HD TVs
最先进驱动的屏幕
have fill rate of 475 megapixels
拥有每秒 4.75 亿像素
per second.
的填充率
Those numbers are already so big
这些数据已经过于大了
that game developers use
以至于游戏开发者
different tweaks to reduce this
做出了不同的改进 来降低这一填充率
Now, let's see how Vive Pro
接下来让我们看看 Vive Pro
compares to those numbers.
在这些数据上的对比情况
Vive Pro has a normal fill rate
Vive Pro 拥有正常的填充率
of 775 megapixels per second,
为每秒 7.75 亿像素
and if you add to that four
如果你增加
times multi-sampling [inaudible]
4 倍多样本抗锯齿
or bigger scaling rate, this
或者更大的缩放率
number will grow even more.
这一数据就会变得更大
That is why reducing fill rate
这就是降低填充率
is so important.
为何如此重要
There are multiple techniques
现在已经有多种技术
there and new techniques are
而且每一天都会
made every day.
产生新的技术
So I encourage you to try them
所以我建议你们 把它们都尝试一遍
all, but today we will focus
但是今天我们
only on a few still as they are
只关注其中的一小部分 因为它们
the simplest to implement and
执行起来最为简单
bring nice performance gains.
并能带来不错的性能提升
So we will start with clipping
那么我们先讲讲裁剪
invisible pixels.
不可见的像素
Here, you can see image rendered
这里 你可以看到渲染的图像
for left eye.
它针对的是左眼
But due to the nature of the
但是因为
lens work, about 20% of those
镜头的性质 大约 20% 的
pixels are lost after compositor
像素会在生成器
performs its distortion
执行失真校正后丢失
So on the right, you can see
在右侧 你可以看到
image that will be displayed on
将在通过镜头之前
a panel in a headset before it
展示在头戴式设备面板上
goes through the lens.
的图像
So, the simplest way to reduce
所以 最简单的
our fill rate is to prevent our
降低填充率的方式就是防止我们的
application from rendering those
App 渲染那些
pixels that won't be visible
完全不可见的像素
anyway, and you can do that
你可以
easily by using SteamVR Stencil
通过使用 SteamVR Stencil Mask
Mask.
轻松实现
So we've just saved 20% of our
那么我们刚刚降低了百分之 20 的
fill rate by applying this
填充率 借助了这一
simple mask, and reduce our Vive
简单的遮罩 并将我们 Vive
Pro fill rate to 620 megapixels.
Pro 的填充率降至 6.2 亿像素
Now, we will analyze implication
现在我们来分析一下
of this lens distortion
执行这一镜头失真校正
correction in more detail.
的更多细节
We will divide our field of view
我们可以将我们的视场
into nine sections.
分为九个区域
Central section has field of
中心区域的视野
view of 80 degrees horizontally
水平为 80 度
by 80 degrees vertically, and we
垂直为 80 度
have surrounding sections on the
周围区域
edges and corners.
位于边缘和角落里
We've color tinted them to
我们为它们上了色
better visualize the
从而可以更好地看到
contribution to final image.
它们对最终图像的影响
So as you can see, corners are
正如你所见
almost completely invisible and
角落几乎完全不可见
edges have matched less
和原来的相比
contribution to the image than
边缘对图像的影响
in the original one.
会更小
In fact, if you see this image
事实上 如果你
in the headset, you wouldn't be
在头戴式设备中看这幅图像
able to look directly at the red
你是无法直接看到红色
sections.
区域的
The only way to see them would
可以看到这些图像的唯一方式
be with your peripheral vision.
就是使用你的周边视觉
So this gives us great hint.
这就给了我们很大的启发
We can render those edge and
我们可以通过较低的填充率
corner sections and a reduced
渲染这些边角区域
fill rate, as they are mostly
因为不管怎么说
invisible anyway.
它们几乎不可见
We render the central section as
我们渲染了中心区域
we did before.
如同之前一样
But then we will render vertical
但之后在渲染垂直边缘时
edges with half of the width and
我们会将宽度减半
horizontal sections with half of
对于水平区域
the height.
则将高度减半
And finally, we will render
最后 在渲染角落区域时
corner edges at one-fourth of
我们会将分辨率降至
the resolution.
四分之一
Once our expensive rendering
当我们完成昂贵的
pass is complete, we will
渲染通道之后 我们会
perform cheap upscaling pass
执行廉价的放大通道
that will stretch those regions
让这些区域
back to the resolution at which
拉伸至
they need to be submitted to
需要提交给生成器的分辨率
So you are wondering how much
那么你可能会好奇
we've gained by doing that.
这样我们可以获得多少提升
In case of 80 by 80 degree
对于 80x80 度
central region, we reduced our
的中央区域 我们将我们的
fill rate all the way down to
填充率一下子降到了
491 megapixels per second.
每秒 4.91 亿像素
But you remember that we just
但是你应该记得我们刚刚
talked about clipping invisible
提到了裁剪不可见像素
pixels, so let's combine those
所以让我们
two techniques together.
将这两个技术结合起来
By clipping pixels combined with
通过将像素裁剪
multi-resolution shading, you
和多分辨率变化结合起来
can reduce your fill rate even
你甚至可以进一步将填充率
further to 456 megapixels per
降至每秒 4.56 亿像素
second, and that is not a random
这并不是一个随机数字
In fact, that's a default fill
事实上这是
rate of Vive headset, so by just
Vive 头戴式设备的默认填充率
using those two optimization
所以仅仅通过使用这两项优化技术
techniques, your application can
你的 App 就可以
render to Vive Pro with much
使用与渲染 Vive 头戴式设备时
higher resolution using exactly
所使用的相同图形处理器
the same GPU as it did when
而得到更高的分辨率
rendering to Vive headset.
对 Vive Pro 进行渲染
Of course, you can use those
当然 你也可以
techniques when rendering to
在对 Vive 进行渲染时
Vive as well, which will allow
使用这些技术
you to bring visualize of your
这能让你 App 的视觉化效果
application even further and
更加突出
make it prettier.
更加美观
There is one caveat here.
这里要提醒一下
Multi-resolution shading
多分辨率变化
requires few render passes, so
需要一些新的渲染通道
it will increase your workload
所以它会在几何管线上
on geometric [inaudible], but
增加你的工作负荷
you can easily mitigate that by
但你可以轻松缓解这一问题
just reducing your central
只需将你的中心区域
vision by a few degrees.
降低几度
Here, by just reducing our
这里 仅将我们的中心视野
central vision by 10 degrees,
降低了 10 度
we've reduced fill rate all the
我们就将填充率一下子降低到了
way to 382 megapixels per
每秒 3.82 亿像素
And if your geometry workload is
而且如果你的几何图形的工作负荷
really high, you can go further,
非常高 你可以更进一步
and experiment with lower fill
尝试更低的填充率
rate, lower regions, that will
更低的区域
reduce fill rate even more.
这会将填充率降得更低
In case of 55 by 55 degrees
对于 55x55 度的
central region, 80% of your
中心区域 你百分之 80 的
[inaudible] eye movement will be
眼部动作仍然会
still inside this region, but
位于这一区域之中 但是
we've reduced our fill rate by
我们将我们的填充率
more than half, to 360
减少了一大半
megapixels per second.
降至每秒 3.6 亿像素
So of course there are different
当然 还有其他
ways to implement
方法可以实现
multi-resolution shading.
多分辨率变化
And you will get different
而且你会从中获得
performance gains from that.
不同的性能提升
So I encourage you to experiment
所以我建议大家
with this technique and try what
尝试这一技术
will work for you best.
看看什么最适合你
So let's summarize everything
下面让我们来总结一下
that we've learned during this
我们在本次会议中 学到的所有内容
We've just announced plug and
我们刚刚公布了针对 Vive Pro 头戴式设备
play support for Vive Pro
的即插即用支持
Headsets, and introduced new
并且介绍了
Metal 2 features that allow you
Metal 2 的新特性 它们能使你
now to develop even more
开发更多的
advanced VR applications.
先进的 VR App
And I encourage you to take
然后我建议大家
advantage of multi-GPU
利用多图形处理器配置
configurations, as they are
因为它们现在
becoming common on other
在 Apple 平台上变得越来越常见
You can learn more about this
你可以通过这个链接
session from this link, and I
了解有关本次会议的更多内容
would like to invite all of you
我想邀请大家
to meet with me and my
在 Metal 4 VR 实验室里
colleagues during Metal 4 VR
和我以及我的同事见面
Lab, that will take place today
时间就定在今天
at 12:00 p.m. in Technology Lab
中午 12 点 地点在 6 号
6.
科技实验室
Thank you very much.
非常感谢大家
[ Applause ]
[ 掌声 ]